"Previously
on the mentalist..."
"Ten years ago, the serial killer
known as Red John"
"Killed my wife and daughter."
"We've been hunting
for him ever since."
We call ourselves
the Blake association.
"Well, who else
is in the association?"
Cops, judges, FBI agents...
Anyone in law enforcement
that needs a secret covered up.
A secret society
of dirty cops.
And Red John's a member.
Kira Tinsley told me something
before she passed.
She told me that her killer...
Red John...
Has a tattoo...
Three dots on his left arm.
So who's Red John?
Today we're pleased
to announce
That we...we finally have
a name, a face.
The director of the division
of law enforcement
Gail Bertram, is Red John.
I am holding in my hand
a writ
from a federal judge.
The FBI is closing down
your organization right now.
We're done. There's
nothing more to do here.
"You're not quitting.
I don't believe it."
It's out of our hands
for now.
I'll be in touch. Okay?
I'm sorry.
For everything.
Lisbon.
Glad you can join us.
- Traffic.
- Hmm. Where's Jane?
He'll be in to see you
as soon as he's able.
This way.
Please, take a seat.
Boy, this is a mess, huh?
A big mess.
- Look, I think we all...
- you can talk later.
Now I understand...
You must all feel scared
Nervous.
Don't know what in the hell
is gonna happen next, right?
- Agent...
- so let me explain what's next.
Over the next few days
we will be talking
to each of you...
individually.
You are entitled to bring along
an attorney
or a union rep,
should you so choose.
Why would we need an attorney?
Well, let's look at this
from our perspective, Kimball.
Your boss Bertram
is a criminal.
Makes sense that you
might be one, too.
We will be looking very closely
at all of you.
If you have ever done anything
even remotely questionable
we will find out
and we will prosecute.
Unless, of course
we feel very, very comfortable
with your cooperation.
Then you got
a little wiggle room.
"The FBI is overseeing"
"an international manhunt"
"for prominent Sacramento
law enforcement official"
"Gail Bertram."
"FBI sources confirm
that Bertram"
"is believed to be the notorious
serial killer Red John"
"wanted for a string
of grisly murders"
"across
the California heartland."
Hey, man.
How's it going?
Do you have a pay phone?
It's right back there.
Thank you.
Hey, Ali, how you doing?
Uh, give me a pick 6...
and one of those
pineapple cheroots.
Pick 6. Cheroot.
Hello?
"Hello, Patrick."
I don't have to use
a funny voice, do I?
You know who this is.
Yes, I do.
It's weird, huh?
'cause the last time we...
Put your hands up...
"Hello?"
- "Hello?"
- Thanks.
- No problem.
- "Hello? Bertram? Hello?"
Clear, sir.
No kidding.
Where is he?
If you're asking about Jane,
I don't know.
- Hmm.
- Did you check upstairs?
Yeah.
You know, maybe
you haven't heard.
About an hour ago,
Gail Bertram
Killed a cop at a gas station
in East Sac.
I heard.
Did you hear what Bertram was
doing at the gas station?
No.
Using a pay phone.
Guess who he was calling.
I'm gonna guess Jane.
Ahh. Yeah. So where is he?
I don't know.
I think you do.
I can't help
what you think.
I think your boyfriend
is colluding
With a dangerous fugitive.
I think
he is up to his neck
In this Blake association
craziness
and probably you are, too.
I'm not. He's not.
Jane can't help
who calls him
and he's not my boyfriend.
It's a damn shame, Teresa.
By all accounts...
you were a good cop.
I still am.
"Hey, boss!"
Rigsby?
Is it safe?
Yeah. What are you doing?
We heard about what Bertram
did this morning.
We heard the FBI
were looking for us.
So what now? You're hiding
in the parking lot?
No. No, we're not hiding.
We're just... Laying low.
Well, we're safe for now.
There's no arrest warrant
that's put out for us
just yet.
Give 'em time.
Where's Jane?
- Don't ask.
- She just did.
Listen to me.
The C.B.I. is gone now.
We're on our own. You need
to protect yourselves.
You don't know where Jane is,
you don't know what he's doing
and you don't wanna know,
you understand?
Yes, boss.
- Yes, boss.
All right then.
But I am not your boss anymore.
That's the point.
We're on our own.
Yeah, we get it.
So where is he?
Hey.
You're a wanted man.
Well, I like to think so.
Seriously. Abbott put
an actual warrant out on you.
Eh. It's not the first time.
So you gonna tell me,
or what?
Oh, yeah. Uh...
Bertram called me.
- I know.
- Mm.
What did he say?
Well, whatever he wanted to say,
he didn't have time.
Why the hell is he still here?
What does he want?
I'm guessing he'll call back
soon and tell me.
Your phone's not safe.
The FBI...
Yeah, they have a tap
on the line.
But they don't have
a trace yet.
If they had a trace,
then I'd be arrested already.
Maybe so, but sooner or later,
they'll get a trace on you.
I know.
But I can't get rid of my phone
until Bertram calls.
It's all very suspenseful.
- What does he want?
- Who?
- Bertram.
- We'll see.
Now you're being evasive.
What beady little eyes
birds have.
Tiny dinosaurs, you know?
I know.
I know you know
what he wants.
What does he want?
Hello?
"Oh, sorry I had to
hang up on you."
It's been a busy day.
Yeah, no problem. You know,
this phone is not safe.
Let me call you back
in a moment.
Yeah.
What'd he say?
Just a second.
Hey. How you doing?
- I'll give you $100 for that phone.
- Huh?
$200 for that phone.
What's the catch?
No catch.
$300 plus...
A replacement phone.
Uh, okay.
Yeah, dude, I'll call you
right back.
Pleasure doing business
with you.
Thanks, man.
Mm-hmm.
What did he say?
Hello?
"Look, I think we should
meet and talk."
- Just the two of us.
- What, like a date?
Yes...
No.
Look, the game is over.
I'd call it
a very honorable tie.
"And now that it's over"
"I really think that
we should talk."
You know, a truce.
No weapons, no tricks.
Just talk.
Then we both walk away.
Talk. About what?
Well... Everything.
I think we both could use
a little closure, don't you?
It has to be today.
You know, now.
I'm kind of
pressed for time.
How do I know I can trust you?
Ah, don't be timid now, Patrick.
I could have Killed you many
times, and I haven't, have I?
Okay. When and where?
Excellent.
I'll be at the Fremont Park
fountain in half an hour.
No. Don't know it.
Central bus station.
- "North entrance."
- Nah, there's too many people.
There's too many cops.
You know Alexandria Cemetery?
Of course I do.
Yeah, there's a chapel
by the western gate.
That...that'll do.
Half an hour.
Don't be late.
I can't wait around.
Half an hour.
What'd he say?
He wants to meet with me.
It's a trap.
Probably.
Well, what are you
gonna do?
- I'm gonna meet him.
- You can't.
Trust me,
I know what I'm doing.
Jane, don't do this.
Think about it.
The FBI is gonna get
Bertram soon enough.
I don't want the FBI
to get him.
You knew this day
was coming.
It's here.
- Let me come with you.
- No, I don't want you involved.
- Involved? I am involved.
- Not anymore.
I'm gonna need
to borrow your gun.
My gun?
Yes, your gun. I'm not gonna use it.
Just a prop.
Teresa, trust me, please.
Just trust me.
Thank you.
Like that way.
Thanks.
Where's the man in charge here?
Where is Abbott?
Get down on your knees. Keep your hands
where I can see them.
Where is Abbott?
I-I have to go.
All right, take it down
a notch, people.
He's not al Capone.
Abbott, please listen to me.
I can tell that you're
a man of honor.
On my honor, I will
give myself up in an hour.
But right now I just...
I just need...
Just...
Forget it.
No. No, no, no, no.
No, tell me.
Come on.
No, what do you need?
What do you need, huh?
You need an hour?
For what?
Where are you going?
Who are you gonna go meet?
No?
Well, let's take a trip
downtown, shall we?
Hey.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
No. You can let her go.
Hi, Miss Lisbon.
Do me this one favor,
Abbott, cop to cop.
Let him go, and I swear
I will bring him back later.
Not happening.
And what is all this urgency
I'm hearing here? Hmm?
Oh. You made a plan
with Bertram.
Is that it?
Is that what you did?
Please, Abbott.
FBI! Back it off!
- CBI. Back it up yourself.
- What's this?
Let him go, Abbott.
He's done nothing wrong.
Hey, guys.
You know, I... it's good
to see you.
I hate to bring you down,
but there is no CBI.
That badge is a toy
and you're all impersonating
officers of the law.
Whatever. Let him go.
Are you mad-dogging me
right now?
The FBI?
You say you're legit FBI,
but how do we know?
Yeah, you could be members
of the Blake association
for all we know.
We're not.
Prove it.
Your man Reede smith
was a member. Why not you?
And how do we know
Jane's not in danger?
That's absurd.
I'm sorry, agent Abbott
but it is our duty
to protect this man
until we're assured
his safety.
Hey. Let him go.
Oh, whoa, whoa.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
No, no, no, no, no.
It's all right.
Just stand down.
Stand down, guys. No bloodshed
required. It's cool.
Let him go.
Take my car.
Sir?
It's okay.
Thank you, guys!
We done?
He's gone. We're done.
Hmm.
Arrest them.
Put your guns
down on the ground...
Slowly.
Do as he says.
Go track
agent Lisbon's vehicle.
Yes, sir.
You put a bug on my car?
How do you think
we found Jane?
I said I was glad
to see you people
Because I knew you would
screw up
And make my life easy.
And you did just that.
Thank you.
Arrest her.
Come on.
"He wasn't ready for it."
"No."
"Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo.
Check it out. Whoa!"
"Check this out."
What's up?
Uh, could you guys keep an eye
on my car for me, please?
Sure, I'll watch it.
Thank you.
Let's go.
Yeah, man, no worries.
"Yeah! Ha ha ha ha!"
Hey there.
Uh...
Sorry to bother you, ma'am.
Uh, long story.
Uh, I need...I need a ride,
if you're willing.
"This is unit 4.
We have the vehicle in sight"
"Stationary
on fifth and Sherman."
Stay back, stay back.
This could be the meet.
"What the heck?"
Unit 4,
what's the situation?
Unit 4, respond, damn it.
"Boss, it was some kids
in Lisbon's car."
"Jane wasn't there."
"We don't have Jane.
Repeat. We don't have Jane."
"Do you co..."
Don't dig yourself
any deeper.
Where'd he go?
I don't know.
You guys really have
a death wish, don't you?
Sir, we really don't know.
Mm-hmm.
"Sir"? Why the hell
are you calling him "sir"?
Oh, calm down, Dillinger.
We're under arrest here.
We might as well be civil.
Why? You think you'll get
a nicer cell?
"Muchas Gracias, Aurelio."
Hey, Patrick.
I'm gonna need to search you
for weapons.
So you can go ahead,
put your hands up.
Worth a shot.
You can go in now.
Patrick.
Thank you for being
so punctual.
You lied to me.
Oh.
Well... as did you.
What a couple of scamps
we are, huh?
I promise that is the last lie
that I will ever tell you.
So...
First things first.
You and the feds have made
a big mistake.
I'm not Red John.
What?
I-I'm sorry to disappoint you
but I'm just
a humble foot soldier
in the Blake association.
Red John is one of
the top brass.
I'm not sure I believe you.
Well...
that's your privilege, but...
But I am telling you the truth.
You all just jumped
to the wrong conclusion.
Okay, so who is
Red John?
Oh, I have no idea.
No, h... honestly.
No idea.
The association works on
a strictly need-to-know basis.
Supposing what you say is true
then we could have had
this talk on the phone.
Yeah, but if we talked
on the phone
then you... you probably
wouldn't have come to meet me
would you?
And I was told to call you
tell you the game's over,
and arrange a meeting.
Why?
Why am I here?
Please... don't think
for a moment
that I am happy about this.
The association doesn't like
loose ends.
Just hates them.
So...
go on, Oscar.
No, no. Listen. Listen.
Let's...
Let's talk about this.
Just... wait.
Now I am truly sorry, but it is
totally out of my hands.
I always liked you, Patrick.
No. No.
This is not necessary.
We don't...don't...
H... hey...
Thank you, Oscar.
You can wait outside.
Just, uh...
make sure we're left
in peace.
Hello, Patrick.
Hi.
Hey!
Hello?!
Hey, what's going on?
- Grace, what are you...
- Hey!
What...please don't
do that.
You're worse than Cho.
They need to tell us
what's going on.
They don't need
to do anything.
And we can't do anything,
so please just relax.
Relax?
How can I relax?
You know, sometimes I think
you like being helpless.
Okay, fine, I take it back.
Don't relax.
Just break the window
with your forehead
and we'll all jump out
and make a run for it.
Guys, let's try to keep it
together, okay?
Okay, I'm sorry.
"Sorry."
Mullins,
you're from here, yes?
Yes, sir. Over to Lincoln heights.
- Get me a map of Sacramento.
- Yes, sir.
There's one on the computer
in the car.
Paper map.
Paper... map.
Come on. Let's go.
Hey, do you have a paper map?
Well, Patrick, here we are.
Poor fella.
Smart but dumb.
It never occurred to him
that I am
the Blake association.
Why'd you have to kill him?
Everyone thinks
he's Red John, don't they?
So... It would seem
a fitting end to the story
if you two were found dead
together.
No one will look
any deeper.
So I'm supposed to die,
am I?
After all these years
seems kind of unfair.
It's totally fair.
The game's over,
and I won.
It's not a game.
There's a winner and a loser.
That's a game.
It's not a game I asked to play.
No, but you played it
very well nonetheless.
You were fun, challenging.
Thank you.
You probably have a lot
of questions for me, huh?
We have time, if you want.
I have no questions.
You're an evil,
sexually perverted sociopath
with pathetic delusions
of grandeur.
The rest is just details.
"Evil, sexually perverted sociopath"?
Well, I guess I have to
own that, but, uh...
"delusions of grandeur"?
No.
I have no delusions.
I built a secret empire.
I control the lives
of thousands of people.
My word is life and death
and nobody knows who I am.
Now if that's not grandeur
I don't know
what you call it.
I'd call it the ravings
of a squalid egomaniac.
You see?
For no reason at all, you...
You're rude and contemptuous.
That's why your wife
and kid are dead.
Who are you to butt in here
and make obnoxious
judgments about me?
Who are you?
Nobody.
You didn't know me.
You don't know me.
You have no idea.
Here's your problem, Pat.
You're a smart man,
but you are arrogant.
You can't imagine someone
smarter than you.
Which is why I've been
ahead of you
at every step along the way.
You're holding the gun.
You wanna brag?
Go ahead.
I'm not gonna stop you.
You still don't know
how I fooled you, do you?
How did I survive
that bomb?
How did I know all the names
on your list?
Is this what you've been missing?
Appreciation?
Hmm?
Do you want me to applaud?
You have no idea, do you?
I don't know how you got
the list of suspects.
That was a good trick.
But the bomb gag is simple.
There were two explosions.
The first was a concussion bomb,
knocked everyone out.
The second, lethal bomb
that Killed Haffner and stiles
only went off after you
dragged Bertram, Smith, and me
out of harm's way.
Correct.
Faking your own death
was easy.
Brett Partridge was
Blake association.
His job gave him access
To the primary
DNA database.
He switched
your DNA records
With a body
that you had on ice.
A surrogate.
And you brought the body
to my house
In the trunk of your car
and you put it alongside
stiles and Haffner.
Very good.
Your hindsight is 20/20.
Can I show you something?
Sure.
Bread crumbs?
Aah! Aah! Aah!
Birds.
Very clever.
The bomb was a mistake.
It was theater.
I knew that whatever
the truth looked like
the opposite must be true.
Please don't.
Don't kill me.
Oh, now you want mercy?
After all you've done?
You're not like me.
You're a good man.
It'll haunt you.
Oh, I'm not hesitating.
I'm just savoring the moment.
You're Red John.
I have to say
I'm a little disappointed.
Oh, my god!
Help! Please!
He's gonna kill me!
Oh, my god!
I'm a policeman,
and you need to leave.
Sir, I'm sorry, you don't
look like a policeman.
Yes, I am. Just do as I say
and leave right now.
- Please put down that gun.
- You need to go.
Whatever's happened here,
more violence is not the answer.
- No, you don't understand.
- Sir, I do understand.
I know how angry you must...
No, you don't,
and you have to go now!
Sir, in all good conscience...
All right,
so he started out here
and he dumped the car here
at a mini-mall.
So where would you arrange
a meeting?
Someplace with easy access,
in and out
close to the highway.
- Ballpark.
- Too much security.
- What's that?
- Community college campus.
No, that, right there.
That's the Alexandria Cemetery.
Where was Jane's wife Buried?
- What does that have to do...
- Where was she Buried?
Alexandria Cemetery.
Thanks.
Let's go!
Oh, no.
Oh, no. Oh, my god!
"Help! Please! Help!"
Which way?
Over there.
"B" team, canvass this side.
Denyer, you're with me.
Let's go.
- Let's go now. Come on.
- Let's see if he's here.
What was that?
Oh, my...
Oh! Oh, my...oh!
No!
Oh! What's going on?
I'm on the line with the police.
I am police, ma'am.
Let me talk to them.
- Thank you. This way?
- Uh, um, yeah, well...
Ah, hell.
- "911. What's your emergency?"
- Hello. Ma...
- Aah!
- "Hello?"
"911.
What's your emergency?"
Please don't kill me.
Let me live.
"911. What's your emergency?"
Please... Let me live.
I'll tell you how I got
the names on your list.
I don't care.
I-I knew because I have
real psychic...
Shh...
I want you to blink
once for "no"
And twice for "yes."
Are you sorry
that you Killed my wife Angela
and my daughter Charlotte?
Good.
Are you afraid to die?
Don't even think about it.
Lisbon...
It's over. It's done.
I just want you to know
I'm okay.
And I'm gonna miss you.